Guide to the James A. Sewell Photograph Album 1902-1904
Oregon State University Libraries, University Archives
James A. Sewell Photograph Album
circa 1902-1904
Oregon State University Libraries, Special Collections & Archives Research Center University Archives 121 The Valley Library Oregon State University Corvallis, OR 97331-4501 Phone: 541-737-2165 Email: archives@oregonstate.edu Web: http://osulibrary.oregonstate.edu/archives
P 259
Sewell, James A., 1881-1959.
0.1 cubic foot, including 87 photographs 1 oversize box
The James A. Sewell Photograph Album consists of a photographic album assembled by Sewell documenting a wide variety of student activities while he was a student at Oregon Agricultural College at the beginning of the 20th century. Sewell, the grandson of Oregon pioneers Henry Sewell and Isaac Allen, returned to Hillsboro and was a farmer until his death in 1959.
Biographical Note:
James A. Sewell was the son of James H. and Sarah (Allen) Sewell and the grandson of Henry Sewell an Oregon pioneer who settled in Oregon in 1843. James A. Sewell was born on April 18, 1881 in Hillsboro, Oregon and attended Tualatin Academy in the 1899-1900 and 1900-1901 school years. He was a student at Oregon Agricultural College from 1901 to 1903, studying mechanical engineering. He later returned to Hillsboro and was a farmer until his death on October 10, 1959. His name is listed as James Ambrose Sewell in OSU records, but genealogical research shows that he is James Allen Sewell.
The James A. Sewell Photograph Album consists of a photograph album assembled by James A. Sewell and is made up of photographs taken at Oregon Agricultural College in about 1902 to 1904. In addition to portrait and group shots of football team players, these photographs document a football game on the OAC campus, cadet formations on campus, the women’s basketball team, track and field events, and a student trip to the Oregon Coast. The album also includes photographs of the exterior and interior views of campus buildings, men’s and women’s physical education classes, and of the band.
Collection is open for research.
This collection consists of one series: I. Photograph Album. The photographs are described in the order in which they appear in the album. Most of the photographs in the album are numbered and these numbers are given in the detailed description of the collection. The photographs are not in numerical order in the album.
This album was acquired in 2006.
Oregon Agricultural College--Buildings.; Oregon Agricultural College--Students.; Oregon Agricultural College. Cadet Corps.
Corvallis (Or.); Pacific Coast (Or.)
Basketball for women--Oregon--Corvallis.; College sports--Oregon--Corvallis.; College students--Oregon--Corvallis.; College buildings--Oregon--Corvallis.; Student activities--Oregon--Corvallis.; Marching bands--Oregon--Corvallis.; Military education--Oregon--Corvallis.; Physical education and training--Oregon--Corvallis.
Photograph albums.
Colleges and Universities; Sports and Recreation; Student Life; Women; Oregon; Corvallis; Photographs
- Photograph Album, circa 1902-1904; Series I
  - Football team sitting on steps of Mechanical Hall, 1902; 1 (Box 1)
    Samuel Lewis Burnaugh center front; William Gustav Abraham, third row, far left; Albert Burton Bower, second row, second from left
  - Football team, 1902; 2 (Box 1)
    Second athletic field
  - Football team, 1902; 3 (Box 1)
  - Football team, 1902; 4 (Box 1)
  - Two football players, 1902; 5 (Box 1)
  - Four football players, 1902; 6 (Box 1)
  - Five football players, 1902; 7 (Box 1)
  - Five football players, 1902; 8 (Box 1)
    From left to right: William Gustav Abraham; John H. Gault; Sameul Lewis Burnaugh; Albert Burton Bower, Lyman Albert Bundy
  - Football team, 1902; 9
  - Football team, 1902; 10 (Box 1)
  - Second Athletic Field, circa 1902; 11 (Box 1)
    Opposite Armory-Gym. Cauthorn Hall is in the background
  - Men's physical education class, circa 1902; 12
    Held in Armory-Gym
  - Cadets sitting in front of Mechanical Hall, circa 1902; 13 (Box 1)
  - Cadets, holding their hats, in front of Mechanical Hall, circa 1902; 14 (Box 1)
  - Cadets, wearing their hats in front of Mechanical Hall, circa 1902; 15 (Box 1)
  - Mechanical engineering classroom, circa 1902; 16 (Box 1)
    Mechanical Hall
  - Football player, 1903; 21 (Box 1)
    Albert Burton Bower
  - Football player, 1902; 22 (Box 1)
  - Two football players, 1903; 23 (Box 1)
  - Football players, 1903; 24 (Box 1)
  - Mechanical engineering classroom, circa 1902; 17 (Box 1)
  - Woodworking classroom, circa 1902; 18 (Box 1)
  - Football team, 1902; 25 (Box 1)
    Samuel Lewis Burnaugh, center, front row; Albert Burton Bower, fifth from left, front row
  - Football player, 1902; 26 (Box 1)
  - The 02-03 Arrows Basketball team, circa 1903; 28 (Box 1)
    Print partially hand-colored. The Arrows were an early basketball team. Hamon S. Bilyeu, Will Scott, back left to right. Carl "Rat" Rinehart, Claude Vivian "Skeeter" Swann, front left to right.
  - The 02-03 Arrows Basketball team, circa 1903; 29 (Box 1)
    The Arrows were an early OAC basketball team. Will Scott, Hamon S. Bilyeu, Jack Bruce Patterson back, left to front; Carl "Rat" Rinehart, Claude Vivian "Skeeter" Swann, front, left to right
  - Women's basketball team, circa 1903; 33
  - Men's physical education class, circa 1903; 34 (Box 1)
    Students lined up in Armory-Gym
  - Students standing, with arms folded, in Armory-Gym, circa 1903; 35 (Box 1)
  - Men's physical education class, circa 1903; 36 (Box 1)
    Students, lying on stomachs, in Armory-Gym
  - Men's physical education class, circa 1903; 37 (Box 1)
    Students, sitting with hands on waists, in Armory-Gym
  - Basketball team, circa 1903; 38 (Box 1)
    Harry E. Rooper, back, far left
  - Basketball team, 1903; 39 (Box 1)
  - Basketball team, 1903; 40 (Box 1)
  - Basketball team, 1903; 41 (Box 1)
  - Marching band, circa 1903; 42 (Box 1)
  - Marching band, circa 1903; 43 (Box 1)
    Print is identical to 42
  - Women athletes, 1904; 44 (Box 1)
  - Five women athletes, circa 1904; 48 (Box 1)
    Standing
  - Five women athletes, circa 1904; 49 (Box 1)
    Sitting
  - Marching Band, circa 1904; 50 (Box 1)
    Agricultural House in background
  - Cadets, circa 1904; 51
    Marching with rifles
  - Band members, circa 1904; 52 (Box 1)
  - Band members, circa 1904; 53 (Box 1)
    Band marching down Corvallis street
  - Track and field scene, circa 1904; 46
    Sprinters at the start line
  - Band members, circa 1904; 47 (Box 1)
    Print is identical to 52
  - Cadets in field holding rifles, circa 1904; 48
  - Cadets in field with band in the background, circa 1904; 49 (Box 1)
  - Cadets in field firing rifles, circa 1904; 50 (Box 1)
  - Track and field, circa 1904; 51 (Box 1)
  - Track and field, circa 1904; 52 (Box 1)
    Officials, other athletes, and spectators in the background
  - Track and field, circa 1904; 53 (Box 1)
    Runner crossing the finishing line; officials and spectators
  - Track and field, circa 1904; 54 (Box 1)
    Group of runners crossing the finishing line; officials and spectators
  - Cadets marching in field, circa 1904; 59 (Box 1)
  - Cadets marching in field, circa 1904; 60 (Box 1)
    Print is identical to 59
  - Beach scene, circa 1904; 64 (Box 1)
  - Beach scene showing beach, circa 1904; 65 (Box 1)
  - Bare-chested man, circa 1904; 92 (Box 1)
    Facing away,showing off muscles. Wrestlers(?)
  - Mechanical Hall, circa 1904; 82 (Box 1)
  - Potted "Glory of the Pacific" chrysanthemum, 1903; 90 (Box 1)
  - Armory-Gym, circa 1904; 84 (Box 1)
  - Interior scene, circa 1904; 86 (Box 1)
  - Graduation class, circa 1904; 97 (Box 1)
  - Agricultural Hall, circa 1904; 81 (Box 1)
  - Students at coast, circa 1904; 66 (Box 1)
    Students in bathing costumes in surf
  - Ocean seen from boat, circa 1904; 67 (Box 1)
  - Students on the T.M. Richardson, circa 1904; 68 (Box 1)
  - Ocean and beach grasses, circa 1904; 69 (Box 1)
  - Women students on porch, circa 1904; 93 (Box 1)
    Students making daisy chains
  - Benton Hall, circa 1904; 83 (Box 1)
  - Bare-chested man, circa 1904; 91
    Man showing muscles. Wrestler (?)
  - Students in surf, circa 1904; 70
  - Cadets standing at attention in front of Agricultural Hall, circa 1904; 71 (Box 1)
  - Cadets standing at attention, circa 1904; 72 (Box 1)
    Company "C"
  - Cadets standing at attention, circa 1904; 73 (Box 1)
    Company "B"
  - Cadets, standing at attention, circa 1904; 74 (Box 1)
    Company "D"
  - Lady of the Fountain, circa 1902; 85 (Box 1)
    Gift presented to the college by the senior class of 1902
  - Photo of a drawing, circa 1903; 79 (Box 1)
    Drawing of white plumes with words "arrows", "champions", and "Corvallis"
  - Cadets, circa 1904; 75 (Box 1)
    Print is identical to 72
  - Eight cadets standing at attention, circa 1904; 76 (Box 1)
  - Cadets standing at attention, circa 1904; 77 (Box 1)
    Company "A"
  - Cadets, circa 1904; 78 (Box 1)
    Print is identical to 77
  - Cadets, circa 1904; 79 (Box 1)
  - Two bare-chested men, circa 1904; 27 (Box 1)
    Wrestlers (?)
  - River scene with students standing in the background, circa 1904 (Box 1)
  - Four students at the coast, circa 1904 (Box 1)
    Wearing bathing costumes, sitting on log in the surf.